Guide to the New York Times Company records. Arthur Hays Sulzberger papers
New York Public Library
- Series II. Subjects, 1823, 1858, 1875, 1891, 1895, 1900-1910, 1916-1972, 1978-1999, n.d; 210.75 boxes, 9 volumes
  - Pictures
    - Of AHS
      These folders contain photographs of AHS, alone and with others, and of other people, in a few instances with related notes and correspondence. This is not a comprehensive collection, many other pictures are filed in the appropriate subject folders, and others are in the books and albums of the Book File. Included are portraits of AHS (1920s-1964), portraits of AHS in uniform, (1917-1918), childhood portraits, correspondence and photographs of portraits of AHS (1944, 1958-1962), photographs of AHS's self-portrait in various stages (1941), portraits and snapshots of AHS and IOS (1921-1961), family portrait at AHS's and IOS's wedding (1917), portraits of AHS with his grandchildren (1944, 1952-1953), portrait of AHS with his mother and his brothers, Leo and David, the three men in uniform (1917 or 1918), and photographs of AHS with other people, inlcuding John Foster Dulles (1956), Syngman Rhee (1954), Grayson Kirk (1952), Chiang Kaishek (1952), Carlton R. Safford (1951), the Duke of Windsor and others (1946), and Clark Gable and Myrna Loy (probably 1930's).
      - General, 1935, 1944-1972, 1999 (Box 229, Folder 6-8)
      - Colgate University, American Newspaper Publishers Association dinner, and unidentified events, 1954, 1959, n.d (Box 229, Folder 11)
      - Diverse events, 1939-1954 (Box 229, Folder 12)
      - Photographs of paintings, 1941, 1944 (Box 229, Folder 13)
      - Portraits
      - 1895, 1901, 1917-1964, n.d. (Box 230, Folder 1-4)
      - 1940s-1950s (Box 294, Folder 6)
      - 1950s (Box 291, Folder 8)
      - Snapshots, 1935, 1949, 1952, n.d (Box 230, Folder 5)
      - With family members, 1917-1961, n.d. (Box 229, Folder 9)
      - With others
      - 1917 (Box 294, Folder 6)
      - 1920-1956, n.d. (Box 229, Folder 10)
    - Of others
      These folders contain photographs of notable persons and NYT staff members. Folders 290.8 and 290.3 contain lists of the people pictured.
      - 1921-1959, n.d. (Box 291, Folder 1-4)
      - 1929-1964, n.d. (Box 290, Folder 3-9)
  - Piedmont College, 1954 (Box 230, Folder 6)
  - Pierpont Morgan Library, 1954, 1959 (Box 230, Folder 7)
  - The Pilgrims, 1933, 1947-1955 (Box 230, Folder 8)
  - Pioneer Bank (Chattanooga), 1935-1940 (Box 230, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh, University of, 1958 (Box 230, Folder 10)
  - Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, 1927-1932 (Box 230, Folder 11)
  - Planned Parenthood, 1942-1967 (Box 230, Folder 12)
  - Plans and Research Department, 1959 (Box 230, Folder 13)
  - Plant Protection, 1956-1958, 1967 (Box 230, Folder 14)
    Includes memoranda about measures to prevent pilferage, assaults, and other crimes.
  - Plastic Wrappers, 1959-1960 (Box 230, Folder 15)
    Includes memoranda and reports on the use of polyethylene wrappers for Sunday issues.
  - The Players, 1941, 1947-1952 (Box 230, Folder 16)
  - PM Daily, 1939-1948 (Box 230, Folder 17)
  - Poetry
    - General, 1919, 1924, 1936, 1942, n.d (Box 230, Folder 18)
      Includes poems by diverse authors, found among AHS's papers without explanation of their significance.
    - Published in The Times, 1932, 1948-1961 (Box 230, Folder 19)
      Includes correspondence about a request for permission to publish a book of selected poems from the NYT, memoranda about the fee paid for poems (1932), and memoranda about the quality of the published poems and proposals to discontinue them (1948-1961).
    - Written by AHS
      These folders contain poems written by AHS for family occasions, to friends and acquaintances, to associates at the NYT, and about events in the news and in his personal life. In many instances original drafts and revisions are included, as are notes and correspondence pertaining to the poems. In a few instances, poems by others that prompted AHS to write a poem in response are also included.
      - Children, 1933-1967 (Box 231, Folder 1)
        Includes poems to or about AHS's children and grandchildren.
      - Dogs, 1954-1962 (Box 231, Folder 2)
        Includes poems about AHS's and other family members' dogs.
      - Friends and Acquaintances, 1927 (Box 291, Folder 9)
        Includes poems to or about friends and acquaintances.
      - General, 1927-1966 (Box 231, Folder 3)
      - Health, 1937-1965 (Box 231, Folder 4)
        Includes poems about AHS's illnesses and medical treatment.
      - Iphigene Ochs Sulzberger, 1924-1966 (Box 231, Folder 5)
        Includes poems to or about IOS, many for birthdays, wedding anniversaries, or accompanying gifts.
      - Miscellaneous, 1931-1965, n.d. (Box 231, Folder 6)
        These poems range from humorous verses about trivia, to poems about AHS's travels abroad, to meditative and philosophical poems.
      - New York Times, 1904, 1926-1963 (Box 231, Folder 7)
        Includes poems to NYT associates or about the paper, including several poems written to his secretaries, The Harem, the poem published in the NYT for which he won honorable mention in the Publisher's Awards, with related correspondence and a poem complaining about having to pay the tax on his prize, and memoranda about Milton Bracker's proposal for a bulletin board for the display of poems written by employees, with the introductory poem by AHS.
      - Other Relatives, 1931-1967 (Box 231, Folder 8)
        Includes poems to or about AHS's brothers and other relatives.
      - Parents
        Includes poems to or about AHS's parents and parents-in-law.
      - 1924-1935 (Box 231, Folder 9)
      - 1928 (Box 293, Folder 10)
      - Politics, 1943-1964 (Box 231, Folder 10)
        Includes poems about political issues and current affairs.
      - WQXR, 1947-1958 (Box 231, Folder 11)
        Includes poems about WQXR and Music.
  - Poker and Pretzel Club, 1932-1946, 1951, 1962 (Box 231, Folder 12)
    Includes letters and other papers concerning the activities of the club, which was composed of close friends of AHS.
  - Poland, 1930-1965 (Box 231, Folder 13)
  - Police Athletic League, 1943-1944, 1955-1959 (Box 231, Folder 14)
  - Policy Statements
  - Political Action Committee for Palestine, 1946-1948 (Box 231, Folder 15)
  - Political Views of AHS, 1931-1961 (Box 232, Folder 1)
    This folder contains diverse letters and memoranda in which AHS discusses general political trends in the United States, ranging from the effects of the Great Depression, through the Franklin D. Roosevelt years and the World War II era, to his growing conservatism in the late 1950s. Included is a letter stating his rule of not becoming publicly involved in political activities (1957).
  - Polk, George, Memorial Awards
  - Polls
  - Poor Richard Club
    - General, 1943, 1951, 1954 (Box 232, Folder 2)
    - Medal, 1951 (Box 279)
  - Popular Mechanics, 1952 (Box 232, Folder 3)
  - Population Council, 1956 (Box 232, Folder 4)
  - Port of New York Authority, 1932, 1947-1961 (Box 232, Folder 5)
  - Portsmouth Times (Virginia), 1956 (Box 232, Folder 6)
  - Portugal, 1950-1962 (Box 232, Folder 7)
  - Postage Stamps, 1951-1965 (Box 232, Folder 8)
  - Postal Rates, 1942, 1947, 1956-1959 (Box 232, Folder 9)
  - Postal Services, 1949-1957 (Box 232, Folder 10)
  - Prague Bureau, 1938-1939 (Box 232, Folder 11)
    Includes correspondence with G. E. R. Gedye about establishing the bureau and abandoning it after the German invasion.
  - Prayers, 1958, 1967 (Box 232, Folder 12)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1953-1954 (Box 232, Folder 13)
  - Presbyterian Hospital
  - Preservation of Newspapers
  - President of The New York Times Co.
  - President's Birthday Ball
  - President's Committee on Scientists and Engineers, 1957-1958 (Box 232, Folder 14)
  - President's Council on Youth Fitness, 1959 (Box 232, Folder 15)
  - Presidential Elections, 1924, 1936, 1947-1952 (Box 232, Folder 16)
    Includes letters, memoranda, and other documents about the national conventions, including television coverage and AHS's attendance, and about broadcasts of the election results.
  - Presidential Inauguration
  - Press Association, Inc., 1943-1952 (Box 232, Folder 17)
    Includes letters and memoranda about the formation of Press Association, Inc. as a subsidiary of the Associated Press to supply news bulletins to radio stations. Also included are notices and minutes of board and stockholders' meetings and semi-annual financial reports.
  - Press Wireless, Inc.
    These folders contain correspondence, memoranda, and other documents pertaining to Press Wireless, the communications company owned by the NYT, other newspapers and the major wire services. They deal with its operations, services, rates, Federal Communications Commission regulations, management, organization, labor relations, and finances. Includes letters and memoranda about the western stockholders' proposals to liquidate the company and sell its Long Island Properties at a profit, the NYT's opposition to this and counterproposals, including a plan to acquire the western stockholders' shares and expand operations (1955-1956), letters and memoranda about the company's reorganization under the Bankruptcy Act and financial difficulties both preceding and following it (1947-1953), memoranda about the United States Army's refusal to let Press Wireless operate in Korea during the Korean War (1950), memoranda about a strike by the American Communications Association and copy of arbitration award (1946), memoranda about the use of Press Wireless facilities during World War II (1944-1945), letters and memoranda about the feud between Joseph Pierson, president of Press Wireless, and Fred Meinholtz, Press Wireless' secretary (1941), memoranda about picture transmission (1938, 1940), memoranda about the unionization of staff at the Long Island installations (1940), memoranda about strikes at the San Francisco and Honolulu facilities (1938-1939), and memoranda about competition from United Press (1938).
    - 1947-1962 (Box 232, Folder 18-19)
    - 1930, 1937-1946 (Box 233, Folder 1-4)
  - Pressmen
  - Previews Inc., 1955 (Box 233, Folder 5)
  - Price Brothers & Co., Ltd.
  - Price Paper Corporation, 1963-1968 (Box 233, Folder 6)
  - Princeton Inn, 1951 (Box 233, Folder 7)
  - Princeton University, 1931, 1940-1964 (Box 233, Folder 8)
  - Printers Ink, 1953-1959 (Box 233, Folder 9)
  - Printers Pension Corporation, 1947 (Box 233, Folder 10)
  - Printing Machinery
  - Private Dining Rooms
  - Production Technology
  - Prohibition
  - Project Hope, 1960 (Box 233, Folder 11)
  - Promotion Department
  - Propaganda, 1924, 1937-1941 (Box 233, Folder 12)
    Includes a journalism student's questions about the menace of propaganda and newspapers' responsibilities in relation to it and AHS's reply, which was not sent at ASO's direction (1924) and correspondence with and about the Institute for Propaganda Analysis and its criticisms of the NYT and newspapers generally (1937-1941).
  - Protestant Council of the City of New York, 1958 (Box 233, Folder 13)
  - Protestant Digest, 1941 (Box 233, Folder 14)
  - Public Ledger (London), 1950 (Box 233, Folder 15)
  - Public School P. S. 111, NYC (Adolph S. Ochs School)
  - Publisher, 1950, 1954, 1959-1961 (Box 233, Folder 16)
    Includes AHS's explanation of the role of a publisher, in response to inquiries, AHS's article in Times Talk, on OED's succeeding him as Publisher, outlining qualities desired in a publisher (1961).
  - Publishers Association of New York City, 1925, 1931-1967 (Box 233, Folder 17)
  - Publishers' Auxiliary, 1951-1962 (Box 233, Folder 18)
  - Puerto Rico, 1948-1966 (Box 233, Folder 19)
  - Pulitzer Prizes
    - General
      Includes letters, memoranda, and clippings about nominations of the NYT and staff members, awards to the NYT, nomination and award procedures and criteria, the American Society of News Editors' role and Arthur Krock's service on the Advisory Board, letters congratulating the NYT on awards, nominations of non-NYT articles by AHS, and AHS's letters congratulating NYT winners and their replies.
      - 1948-1968 (Box 233, Folder 20-21)
      - 1928-1947 (Box 234, Folder 1-2)
    - Closed memoranda, 1964 (Box 297, Folder 2)
  - Pulpit Digest, 1956 (Box 234, Folder 3)
  - Punch, 1937 (Box 234, Folder 4)
  - Puns
  - Putnam Trust Co.
  - Puzzles, 1924-1967 (Box 234, Folder 5)
    Includes notes and letters on diverse puzzles published in the NYT and on puzzles invented or collected by AHS or Charles Merz, Editor & Publisher article noting Sunday crossword puzzle created by AHS and Charles Merz (1942), memorandum and letters about the first and last Double Crostics by Elizabeth S. Kingsley (1943, 1952), memoranda about syndicating crossword puzzles and using them to promote the NYTimes (1953-1955), and a memorandum about jigsaw puzzle using a NYT front page (1967).
  - Pynson Printers, Inc.
  - Quakers
  - Quotation of the Day
  - Rabbinical Conference of America
  - Race
  - Racial Integration
  - Racketeering in Labor Movement
  - Radiation, 1935 (Box 234, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence about the suggested treatment of cancer and other diseases by ingesting or injecting radium.
  - Radio, 1932-1962 (Box 234, Folder 7-8)
    These folders contain letters, memoranda, reports, and clippings about the radio industry, especially its news, editorial broadcasts, the issue of newspapers and news services supplying material for these, and the NYT's reports about the industry. Included are correspondence about offers of stations for acquisition by the NYT (1940, 1943, 1956), memoranda about the start of a daily column about radio by Jack Gould (1947), correspondence about the issue of government licensing (1946), survey of New York area stations (1939), a transcript of a broadcast by NBC, "The New York Times Goes to Press" (1937).
  - Radio and Television Programs Listings, 1932, 1951-1968 (Box 234, Folder 9)
  - Radio City Music Hall, 1954-1959 (Box 234, Folder 10)
    Includes Turner Catledge's memorandum on the policy of reviewing stage shows.
  - Radio City Synagogue, 1957-1958 (Box 234, Folder 11)
  - Radio Corporation of America, 1940, 1958, 1965 (Box 234, Folder 12)
  - Rag Paper Edition, 1947-1953 (Box 235, Folder 1)
  - Railroad Delivery of The Times
  - Rainsford House, 1946-1952 (Box 235, Folder 2)
  - Raleigh News and Observer, 1940 (Box 235, Folder 3)
  - Rand School of Social Science, 1948 (Box 235, Folder 4)
  - Random House, 1960 (Box 235, Folder 5)
  - Raymond Service, Inc., 1958 (Box 235, Folder 6)
  - Read House, 1935-1940 (Box 235, Folder 7)
  - Reader's Digest, 1947-1960 (Box 235, Folder 8)
  - Readership Surveys
  - Reading, 1949-1950 (Box 235, Folder 9)
  - Real Detective, 1937 (Box 235, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate News, 1937-1965 (Box 235, Folder 11)
    Includes letters and memoranda about the coverage of real estate news, layout, illustrations, and changes in the Sunday section, about an award by the National Association of Real Estate Boards to the NYT for the best real estate page (1945), and about identifying architects in news stories and picture captions (1937, 1942).
  - Ralits, 1953-1958 (Box 235, Folder 12)
  - Recipes, undated (Box 235, Folder 13)
  - Reconnaissance Balloons
  - Reconstruction Finance Corporation, 1951 (Box 235, Folder 14)
  - The Recorder, 1950-1954 (Box 235, Folder 15)
  - Recording for the Blind, Inc., 1957-1966 (Box 235, Folder 16)
  - Red Cross
    AHS was very active in the Red Cross. He was elected an Incorporator (1937), a member of the Central Committee and of the board of the New York Chapter (1942), and a member of the board of governors (1951). He headed the Blood Donor Committee of the New York Chapter and was a member of the Future Planning Committee. These folders contain documents relating to all his activities except the blood donor campaign (the documents relating to that are under Blood Banks). They concern Red Cross operations within the United States and abroad, especially during World War II, fund-raising and publicity, and AHS's and the NYT's roles in both, changes in the administration and policies of the Red Cross, recruiting and training of volunteers, certificates honoring AHS and the NYT for their contributions, and criticism of Red Cross policies and activities. Included are letters about AHS's Red Cross tours in England, 1942, and the USSR, 1943, and in Pacific areas, 1944-1945 (1961, 1971, 1973), AHS's memorandum about his opposition to Basil O'Connor's reappointment as national chairman and AHS's failure to win re-election to the Central Committee (1957), letters and memoranda about the lag in NYT employees' contributions (1957), AHS's resignation from the board of the New York Chapter and OED's election in his stead (1947), correspondence and clippings about the Central Committee's dissension over O'Connor's reappointment and AHS's failure to be re-elected to the Committee (1945-1946), letters and other documents about Red Cross fund-raising agreement with committees of the American Federation of Labor (AFL) and the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) (1945), letters, reports, memoranda, and other documents about AHS's Red Cross survey trips, with Turner Catledge to the Pacific in 1944 and with James Reston to England, Russia, and Mediterranean-Near East areas in 1943, correspondence with persons he met during those trips is included though it may not deal with Red Cross matters, photographs (1943-1945), letters, memoranda, and reports by Catledge and others about Red Cross efforts to get supplies to prisoners of war in Japanese-held areas, letters about Catledge's series of articles on Red Cross operations, letters about AHS's speech to the North Atlantic Region conference of the Red Cross (1943-1944), letters, cables, reports and other documents about AHS's trip to Britain to check on Red Cross operations there, correspondence with military and political leaders, reports, photographs (1942), correspondence about a United States bill to restrict use of the red cross symbol to the Red Cross (1942, 1944), and a report of a committee on Red Cross services to the armed forces (1941-1942).
    - 1945 Apr-1965, 1971-1973 (Box 235, Folder 17-22)
    - 1943-1945 Mar (Box 236, Folder 1-7)
    - 1937-1942 (Box 237, Folder 1-4)
  - Reece Report, 1954-1955 (Box 237, Folder 5)
  - Reforestation Commission, 1929-1931, 1938 (Box 237, Folder 6-8)
    These folders contain correspondence about the work of the New York State Reforestation Commission, of which AHS was a member, reports of the Commission and interested organizations, bills of the State Legislature, publicity releases and pamphlets, and minutes of meetings.
  - Refugees, 1933-1940, 1957-1964 (Box 237, Folder 9)
    Includes letters about aid to refugees from Nazi Germany, memoranda about Camille Cianfarra's report on refugees in Mexico, memoranda about NYT employment of, or attempts to aid, refugees from Hungary and other East European countries.
  - Rehabilitation Medicine
  - Religion, 1920-1963 (Box 237, Folder 10)
    Includes letters, memoranda, and notes expressing AHS's personal beliefs and attitude towards organized religion.
  - Religion in American Life, Inc., 1952, 1958-1968 (Box 237, Folder 11)
  - Religious News, 1934-1962 (Box 238, Folder 1)
    Includes memoranda about NYT coverage of religious news, correspondence with Robert W. Searle about this and possible candidates for the post of religious news editor, and Edwin L. James' reply to a charge of pro-Catholic bias in coverage.
  - Religious News Association, 1933 (Box 238, Folder 2)
  - Religious News Service
  - Remington Rand, Inc., 1953, 1959 (Box 238, Folder 3)
  - Reparations
  - The Reporter, 1954-1957 (Box 238, Folder 4)
  - Reprint Permissions, 1928-1968 (Box 238, Folder 5-13)
    These folders contain memoranda and letters about requests for permission to reprint, in whole or in part, material published in the NYTimes, permission was usually granted unless the NYT had only limited rights to the material or the purpose of the reprint was either propaganda or commercial exploitation.
  - Republic Aviation Corporation, 1958 (Box 238, Folder 14)
  - Research Institute of America, 1954-1960 (Box 238, Folder 15)
  - Residences
  - Restaurant (New York Times), 1937-1968 (Box 239, Folder 1-2)
    Includes memoranda about restaurant operations, staff, food served, changes in decor, prices, and related matters. This file covers the service restaurant, the cafeteria, and the Publisher's and executives' private dining rooms.
  - Restaurants, 1953-1959 (Box 239, Folder 3)
    Includes letters and memoranda about several restaurants and the NYT's restaurant reviews.
  - Retail Dry Goods Association
  - Retirement
  - Reuters, Ltd., 1934, 1945-1964 (Box 239, Folder 4)
    Includes letters and memoranda about the NYT's subscription to Reuters service (1934), arrangements to use Reuters' wire for transmission of NYT copy from London (1945, 1948), Reuters' use of space in the NYT building and the NYT' s London Bureau use of space in Reuters' London headquarters (1947, 1950), AHS's interview with Reuters (1947), Reuters' use of NYT material (1945), and visits by AHS to London and visits by Reuters executives to The Times.
  - Review of the Week, 1930, 1935, 1946-1967 (Box 239, Folder 5-6)
    Includes AHS's memorandum to ASO suggesting a weekly review on Sunday's editorial page (1930), memoranda, distributors' comments, and readers' letters on the first Sunday Review section (1935), and memoranda about the section's size, layout, typography, specific articles, photographs, and other illustrations.
  - Rheinstein Construction Co., Inc., 1939, 1946-1947, 1954, 1960 (Box 239, Folder 7)
  - Rhodes School, 1953 (Box 239, Folder 8)
  - Ridge Ranch School (Paramus, NJ), 1959-1962 (Box 239, Folder 9)
  - Rights and Permissions
  - Riis House, 1946 (Box 239, Folder 10)
  - Riverside Church, 1955 (Box 239, Folder 11)
  - RKO Pathe, Inc.
  - Rochester Institute of Technology, 1943-1953 (Box 239, Folder 12)
  - Rockaway News Supply Co., 1961 (Box 239, Folder 13)
  - Rockefeller Foundation
    AHS was a trustee of the Rockefeller Foundation from 1939 to 1957 and served on the audit and nominating committees. These folders contain documents pertaining to meetings, projects funded by the Foundation, suggestions for activities and policies, nominations to the board of trustees, and investigations by two Congressional committees. Projects sponsored by the Foundation often prompted AHS's suggestions for editorials and news coverage in the NYT. Finally, these papers document the close personal relationship of AHS with other trustees and executives of the Foundation, notably, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dean Rusk, and John S. Dickey. Included are letters about OED's election as a trustee (1960), Rusk's response to AHS's question about passing Foundation reports to NYT personnel (1958), letters about AHS's retirement as a trustee (1957), AHS's personal and confidential letter on four newspaper publishers being considered for election as trustees (1956), letters and other documents dealing with the Reece Committee report on foundations, including AHS's offer to resign from the Foundation because of the report's references to alleged influence by the Foundation on newspapers whose executives were trustees (1954), letters, excerpts from testimony, and other documents dealing with the Cox Committee Investigation (1952), letters about the Kinsey Report (1948-1949), and letters about AHS's nomination to the executive committee and to the board of trustees (1939, 1942).
    - 1952-1964 (Box 239, Folder 14-19)
    - 1939-1951 (Box 240, Folder 1-3)
  - Rockefeller Institute, 1951, 1959 (Box 240, Folder 4)
  - Rogers, Will, Memorial Commission, 1935 (Box 240, Folder 5)
  - Rogers Peet Co., 1953 (Box 240, Folder 6)